# ROMAN FILIPPOV

romanfilippov.inbox@gmail.com · linkedin.com/in/filippovroman

Skilled iOS developer (Objective-C, SwiftUI, UIKit) with over 9 years of expertise and degree in applied mathematics and computer science. I have worked both in teams and as an independent freelancer, building apps from scratch and managing full development cycles.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## SkyTech LLC

April 2021 – November 2024

# **Senior iOS Developer**

- Managed a team of 2 iOS developers, reviewed code, participated in sprint planning.
- Split app into modules, reducing build time by 50% and decoupling the code.
- Migrated from UIKit to SwiftUI, resulting in a more consistent and adaptive UI.
- Migrated to Firebase Auth, resolving SMS confirmation issues across different countries.
- Integrated Firebase Remote Config, resulting in app flexibility without recompilation.
- Implemented app localization, making the app available worldwide.
- Fixed bugs with WebRTC connections, resulting in stable audio/video calls/
- Tech stack: Swift, SwiftUI, Objective-C, MVVM, SQLite, Protobuf, AFNetworking, Starscream, XIB, Swiftgen, Cocoapods, WebRTC.
- App is available in the AppStore

## Upwork.com

October 2018 - March 2021

#### iOS Developer

- Top rated freelancer, 100% job success rate.
- 18 projects, overall feedback score 5.0.
- Full cycle development (costs & features planning, architecture decisions, implementation from scratch).
- Tech stack: Swift, Objective-C, CoreData, Realm, Alamofire, Firebase, AWS, StoreKit, CloudKit, MVVM/MVC, Swiftgen and many more.

#### Forasoft LLC

March 2018 – October 2018

### iOS Developer

- Work in a team of 5 iOS Developers, mentored Junior iOS Developers.
- Developed apps featuring online streaming and audio/video calls.
- Tech stack: Swift, Objective-C, Realm, CocoaPods, Git, JIRA, Jenkins, WebRTC, Alamofire.

## Steppechange LLC

March 2013 - February 2016

### iOS Developer

- Work in a team of 2 iOS Developers.
- Developed apps with messaging features.
- Tech stack: Objective-C, CoreData, Git.

### **EDUCATION**

Aalto University, Helsinki, Finland

2014 - 2016

### Master of Science degree, Service Design and Engineering

• Launched a startup and contributed to MVP development as an iOS developer.

Computer Science Center, St.Petersburg, Russia

2011 - 2014

### Advanced training courses, Software Engineering

• Lectures and seminars were conducted by members of Yandex, HP Labs, JetBrains, and St. Petersburg Academic University.

# Specialist degree, Applied Mathematics and Computer Science

### **LANGUAGES**

- Russian (Native)
- English (C1)

### **SKILLS & OTHER**

**Skills**: Swift, Objective-C, SwiftUI, CoreData, Realm, SQLite, Alamofire, REST, Firebase SDKs, Git, XCTest, Autolayout, UIKit, Protobuf, Websocket, GCD, NSOperation, Concurrency, Cocoapods, Carthage, Swift Package Manager, WebRTC, MVVM, MVC, VIPER, Clean Architecture, SOLID, DRY, KISS.

**Teaching experience**: Conducted a 'Databases and Network Technologies' course for first-year students in 2017.

**Academic Publications**: MOBIQUITOUS 2017 (indexed in scopus):
Authentication and Access Control for Open Messaging Interface Standard.
Authors: Narges Yousefnezhad, Roman Filippov, Asad Javed, Andrea Buda, Manik Madhikermi and Kary Framling.